<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preach'd before the Lord Mayor and Court of Aldermen, June 27, 1680 by Charles Hickman ...</title>
            <author>Hickman, Charles, 1648-1713.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43697</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1895</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18596</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13046380</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13046380</idno>
            <idno type="VID">96925</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43697)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96925)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 742:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preach'd before the Lord Mayor and Court of Aldermen, June 27, 1680 by Charles Hickman ...</title>
                  <author>Hickman, Charles, 1648-1713.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Henry Brome ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Kings, 1st, XVIII, 21 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:96925:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:96925:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preach'd before the Lord Mayor And COURT of ALDERMEN, <hi>June</hi> 27. 1680.</p>
            <p>BY CHARLES HICKMAN, Student of <hi>Chriſt-Church</hi> in <hi>Oxford,</hi> and Chaplain to his Grace the Duke of <hi>Southampton.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Henry Brome,</hi> at the <hi>Gun</hi> in S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1680.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:96925:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <opener>
               <signed>Clayton Mayor.</signed> 
               <dateline>Curia ſpecial. tent. <date>die Dominico quarto die Julij <hi>1680.</hi> Regni Anno<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Regis Caroli ſecundi, Angliae, &amp;c. xxxii.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>THis Court doth deſire Mr. <hi>Hickman</hi> to Print his Sermon Preached on this day ſeven-night at the <hi>Guild-hall</hi> Chappel, before the Lord Mayor and Aldermen of this City.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Wagſtaff.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:96925:3"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:96925:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:96925:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:96925:4"/>
            <head>TO THE Right Honourable S<hi rend="sup">R</hi>s. Robert Clayton, <hi>LORD MAYOR.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ince your Lordſhip has ſentenc'd this diſcourſe to the Preſs, I ſhall no longer diſpute your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands; but according to the true character of an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Subject, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving already aſſerted my liberty in the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of a defence, I muſt leave the final de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination to the Higher powers: Thus manifeſting my Obedience without betraying my Birthright. I know the many cenſures which a diſcourſe of this nature is liable unto,
<pb facs="tcp:96925:5"/> and therefore in publiſhing of it, I have given an inſtance of that ſincerity and boldneſs, to which I exhorted others; but having juſtice on my ſide, and your Lordſhip for my Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, I ſhall need no other Apology to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend me to the favour of <hi>good men,</hi> or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect me from the detractions of the <hi>mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt Obedient and moſt Humble Servant, CHARLES HICKMAN.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:96925:5"/>
            <head>A SERMON ON 1 KINGS xviii. 21.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>And <hi>Elijah</hi> came unto all the people and ſaid, How halt ye between two opinions? <hi>If the Lord be God, follow him, but if Baal, then follow him.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Jews in the days of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Elijah,</hi> lay under the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt preſſures of ſin and judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſeem'd to all men but themſelves not only miſerable but deſperate too: <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> were now become terms of defiance to each other, and though they were alike hated by the Heathens, and their neighbouring Nations ſought occaſion for their ruin, yet neither their publick calamities, nor the private tyes of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanguinity
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:96925:6"/> and friendſhip could refrain them from drawing their ſwords upon themſelves: <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> which was not long ſince the admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and envy of the World, was now become a reproach unto it ſelf, a ſcandal to its Religion, and a joy only to its Enemies, whilſt their home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred diviſions prepar'd them for a forein captivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and they reveng'd upon themſelves the quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels of the Nations which they had driven out; their Kings for many ſucceſſions were ſuch as ſhew'd that God gave them in his anger, and their Chronicles were only the enumeration of the follies, impieties and idolatry both of King and people; therefore was the wrath of God kindled againſt them, and the ſeveral judgments which he puniſhed them withal diſtinguiſh'd their years and made up all the ſignal periods in their late Chronology.</p>
            <p>And as a falling weight gathers ſtrength from it, motion, and the nearer it comes to the ground ſo much the ſwifter it moves, even thus the Jews by the violence of their tranſgreſſions ſeem'd to approach their final ruin, and that the iniquity of <hi>Iſrael</hi> was now full. Time and ſucceſſion had given ſtrength and ſecurity to their ſins, the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God did not bring them to repentance but harden them in their tranſgreſſions, the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:96925:6"/> over their heads were now become as braſs and the Earth under them was iron, the Land that <hi>flowed with milk and honey,</hi> now <hi>withheld her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe,</hi> God did not give his bleſſing; nevertheleſs though their ſoul fainted within them, yet had they courage enough to rebel againſt their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, they forſook the Lord their ſtrength, and they who were wont to go to the houſe of God as friends, now in their divided Tents ſet up the abominations of <hi>Baal,</hi> and conſented only in worſhiping the <hi>fooliſhneſs of the Heathen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus have we a miſerable proſpect of a rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Church and State; for the iniquity of their forefathers their Kingdom was divided, and their own tranſgreſſions had multiplied Gods judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon them; in the hardneſs of their heart they flighted their danger, and in their folly they rejected the Lord from whom alone they could expect redreſs.</p>
            <p>Then ſtood up <hi>Elijah</hi> like fire, and his Word burnt like a Lamp: in the power of the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, he brought their Kings to deſtruction, and the people to the worſhip of the living God: he was ordained for reproofs in thoſe times to pacifie the wrath of the Lords judgments before it brake forth into fury, and to reſtore the Tribes of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Then came <hi>Elijah</hi> unto all the people and ſaid,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:96925:7"/> 
               <hi>If the Lord be God follow him, but if</hi> Baal <hi>then fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which words me may obſerve, 1. a Suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, that there is a God, whither it be the Lord or <hi>Baal.</hi> 2. An Exhortation grounded upon this Suppoſition, and that is twofold.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>If the Lord he God, follow him.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>But if Baal be God, then follow him.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. The Text ſuppoſes that there is a God, whether it be the Lord or <hi>Baal,</hi> and this is a truth ſo manifeſt that the very <hi>Heathens</hi> who had no knowledg of his Name, have confeſs'd there was no Nation ſo barbarous but has conſtantly believ'd his power: the very <hi>Jews,</hi> though the moſt blind and and ſtiff-necked generation, yet never came to that degree of obſtinacy, but that they ſtill acknowledg'd ſome power which they believ'd Divine: for no ſooner did they forſake the Temple of the living God, but they ſet up Altars and Groves to <hi>Baal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the ſuggeſtions of the Atheiſt, that there is no God beſides himſelf, and no other life but this, they are groundleſs and uncertain: all their proofs are founded upon a bare poſſibility, and the belief thereof can never reach higher than o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion: ſuch thoughts are the effects of deep ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance and want of ſenſe, and are only the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:96925:7"/> faint dying hopes of a languiſhing ſinner: for there is none would deny the power of God, but he that through his Vices deſpairs of his mercy. He that can affirm Divinity to be a fancy, and Religion the contrivance of a Politician, may with as much reaſon affirm, that the whole World is but an apparition, that we do but dream of Cities and Palaces, and theſe Walls which we behold are but the phantaſtical deluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of a ſickly brain. He that can deny the being of a God, may alſo deny the being of a Man.</p>
            <p>Again, the opinion of the Atheiſt is not only very unreaſonable but alſo very dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous: for ſuppoſing it were true, that this life de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termines his being (which yet cannot be known till after death) yet when Death has ſwallow'd him up in forgetfulneſs and brought him to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, where then is the reward of his dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous experiment, or who ſhall inherit the praiſe and glory of his notable diſcovery? But if his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion ſhould prove falſe, (as he has great reaſon to ſuſpect from the uncertain grounds of his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief) if Death the Miniſter of God ſhould preach his Goſpel of terrours unto him, and the pains of Hell convince him of his miſtake, what profit has he then of all his travail? the hardneſs of his heart cannot beat back the everlaſting
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:96925:8"/> flames, nor the obſtinacy of his unbelief per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade him out of his ſenſes, though now it per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuades him out of his reaſon.</p>
            <p>Far be it from me therefore, in a Chriſtian Congregation, from endeavouring to convince ſo groſs and abſurd a belief; to confute the error here, is to profane the truth: 'tis an opinion that proceeds not from thoughtfulneſs and ſtudy, but intemperance and vice. Men debauch them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves out of their Religion; and Atheiſm is not the perſuaſion of the man, no nor the belief of the Devil, but the puniſhment of the Beaſt: 'Tis that hardneſs of heart, that reprobate ſenſe to which God delivers up an obſtinate Sinner; 'tis the laſt of Judgments inflicted by God upon him that has refus'd all the methods of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; and therefore to argue a man out of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelity, is to diſpute a Lunatick into his ſenſes, or perſuade a Leper to be clean; they are proof againſt all reaſon, and the Prophet in my Text would not throw away a miracle to reduce them.</p>
            <p>Since therefore God has forſaken him, and delivered him up to the worſt of all evils, that is, to himſelf, let us alſo leave him to purſue his own ruin, ſince he has refus'd inſtruction, and will have none to adviſe; God at length will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waken
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:96925:8"/> him by his thunder, and ſtretch forth the arm of his Vengeance upon him, when there is none to help.</p>
            <p>Suppoſing therefore that there is a God, I come in the next place to conſider what is our duty to him, as it is expreſs'd in the ſecond part of my Text, the exhortation of the Prophet, <hi>If the Lord be God follow him.</hi> From which words I ſhall endeavour to ſhew,
<list>
                  <item>1. What it is to follow the Lord.</item>
                  <item>2. In what manner we muſt follow him; and</item>
                  <item>3. How we may know whether we follow the Lord or not.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>And 1. To follow the Lord is the ſum and ſubſtance of all Religion: For if we conſider him as our Father, then to follow him, is to pay him that honour and reſpect which is due unto a Father; as he is our King, we muſt fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him in a ſubmiſſive obedience to his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands; and as he is our God, we muſt follow him in that worſhip of his Name which he has revealed: But becauſe the latter of theſe is chiefly intended by the Prophet in my Text, therefore it ſhall be the ſubject of my enſuing diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>The notion of a God, as it is infus'd into us by nature, does include in it ſuch tranſcendent
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:96925:9"/> marks of excellency and power, ſuch glorious attributes of juſtice and mercy, that it is not only the duty, but alſo the inclination of man to fall down and worſhip. Yet ſince through the infirmities of our nature, we are incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs'd about with ſuch a cloud of difficulties, that our Devotion may either be too little or too much, leſt our ignorance ſhould betray us either to diſreſpect on the one hand, or ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion on the other, God has made himſelf our Guide unto his Sanctuary; by Apoſtles and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets he has continually inſtructed his Church in what manner he would be worſhip'd, and ſent his only Son to give light unto us that ſat in darkneſs.</p>
            <p>'Tis our duty therefore to turn unto the Lord our God, and make his Will the rule of our acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſince by many and mighty inſtances of his mercy &amp; power he has manifeſted himſelf to be the very God: Let us in all humble obedience fall down &amp; worſhip: Since by his infinite goodneſs he has made himſelf the guide to our devotions, Let us not with the giddy multitude admire the novelties and devices of the Nations, but follow his directions with chearfulneſs and ſubmiſſion, for he is all goodneſs, and cannot deceive us; he alſo is all wiſdom, and cannot be himſelf de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:96925:9"/>
            <p>What folly is it therefore to ſeek after new in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions, and in the blindneſs of our hearts beat in untrodden paths, when God himſelf, who is the light and the truth, has made our way plain before us? Why ſhould we chooſe to perplex our thoughts, and wander by our ſelves, rather than follow the guidance of our God, and the footſteps of our Fathers that went before us? The difficulties and intricacies of our ways are ſufficient of themſelves to exerciſe both our pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and our faith. Why then ſhould we cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate unto our ſelves troubles more and more, and add unto our ſorrow? ſince we muſt neceſſarily paſs through a Wilderneſs before we come into the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> let us <hi>commit our ways unto God,</hi> who brought us hither, and <hi>he will order our goings,</hi> and bring us forth into his pleaſant Land.</p>
            <p>But if we caſt behind us the Counſels and Commands of the moſt High, and truſt to our own inventions; if through the perverſeneſs of our hearts, the boaſtings of our diſcretion, or the preſumption of our vertue, we chooſe our own ways, and our ſoul delighteth in our abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations; God alſo will chooſe our deluſions, and bring our fears upon us.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:96925:10"/>
            <p>For the preſence of God is dreadful, his glory is too great to be rudely invaded by mortal eyes, and his Ark too holy to be touch'd by unskilful hands: Therefore he has ſet bounds to our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, as he did to the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the Mount, leſt they ſhould <hi>preſs forward to gaze upon the Lord, and he break forth upon them, that they periſh.</hi> He has appointed our diſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that we ſhould obſerve in his worſhip, and taught us what an awful reverence we ſhould bear towards him, when we approach unto his Majeſty. We muſt uſe ſuch decent Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies in our Devotion as may ſhew that we are not converſing with fleſh and blood, nor putting up our Petitions to an Earthly Prince, but to an Almighty Soveraign, and the inviſible powers of Heaven and Earth: A rude familia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity is an abomination to him; and though he humbles himſelf to receive our Prayers, yet we ought not therefore to debaſe him in our thoughts, and look upon him for ſuch a one as our ſelves. When we approach unto the preſence of an earthly Prince, we are cautious that we offend him not through any undecent beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, but obſerve all the ceremonies of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs; we ſtudy ſuch poſtures as may expreſs his greatneſs and our humility, and ſuch terms
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:96925:10"/> as may beſt ſet forth our deſires, and reconcile his favour. How is it then that we can ruſh in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the preſence of the Almighty, as a <hi>Horſe ruſhes into the battel,</hi> without either fear or conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and relying only upon a groundleſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence and preſumption? that we ſhould dare to proffer our unſtudy'd Prayers and unſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied perſons unto the God of all Wiſdom, unto whom the moſt corrected of our thoughts are folly, &amp; the beſt of our actions are impure in his ſight. So jealous is God of his honour for the punctual obſervance of his worſhip, that the puniſhment of the <hi>offender</hi> cannot ſufficiently expiate his crime, but he viſits the offence to the <hi>third and fourth Generation;</hi> therefore for the more exact performance of this ſo impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant duty, we muſt obſerve theſe following rules.</p>
            <p n="1">1. We muſt follow the Lord openly with boldneſs and reſolution, as being neither afraid nor aſham'd to own that truth from whence we expect ſalvation. We muſt not hide the Word of God in our hearts, but make profeſſion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of with our mouths, leſt the Scornful and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane ſhould take our ſilence for a perfect ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to their cauſe, and the daughters of the uncircumciſed triumph; leſt the unreprov'd
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:96925:11"/> tranſgreſſors ſhould die in their ſins, and their blood be required at our hands. Why then ſhould we add the guilt of other mens ſins to the number of our own? why ſhould their ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity be our ruin? Therefore, through God our <hi>righteouſneſs,</hi> let us be <hi>bold as a Lion,</hi> and dare to be religious even in a ſinful and adulterous generation; and let the Prophet in my Text be our great example, who alone did withſtand the Congregation of the Prieſts of <hi>Baal,</hi> and brought the whole Aſſembly of <hi>Iſrael</hi> into ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection: He caſt not in his Lot amongſt the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing Idolaters, nor went forth with the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude to their faſhionable devotions, but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood them to the face, and maintain'd the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of his Church when he was the only Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet left therein.</p>
            <p>Nothing can excuſe the cowardice and falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of him who denies or diſſembles that faith which he believes; and if we are aſham'd of Chriſt and his words before men, of us alſo will the Son of man be aſham'd when he cometh in the glory of his Father.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We muſt follow the Lord ſtedfaſtly with conſtancy and perſeverance, not wavering in our belief, nor waxing faint in the day of tryal, but ſtill preſſing forwards in our courſe, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:96925:11"/> with our faith overcoming all the difficulties in our way. O <hi>Elijah,</hi> how waſt thou honour'd in thy wondrous works, and who may glory like unto thee? Such was the aſſurance of our great Prophet, ſo ſtrong and active was his faith, that he made the very laws of nature give place unto it, and brought down fire from Heaven to convince the people.</p>
            <p>Through all the difficulties that attend our faith, and the dangers that threaten the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of it, we muſt ſtill look unto God, who has promis'd that he will never leave us nor for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake us: We muſt not at any time, nor upon any pretence bow down the knee to <hi>Baal,</hi> nor ſhew any compliance with the worſhip of a ſtrange god, leſt our hearts at length ſhould be inclin'd to their folly, and God in his anger give us over to follow their abominations.</p>
            <p>And as we muſt abhor the houſe of <hi>Baal,</hi> ſo we muſt with equal care avoid all falſe ways of ſerving the living Lord, for it matters very much whether we worſhip at the Mount in <hi>Samaria,</hi> or the Temple of <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> and a man may Apoſtatize from the faith with our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing his God: But 'tis much to be fear'd that he who never ſtrains at Hereſie and Schiſm, would ſwallow down infidelity too, ſhould his
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:96925:12"/> intereſt command him, and from paying God a falſe worſhip, would ſoon be brought to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip a falſe God: for how can we expect that God will accept the ſacrifice of our hearts when we come unto him with a lye in our mouths? How can we ſing the Lords ſong in a ſtrange Land, or teſtifie our penitence to God in a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice which is to be repented of? if we deny the neceſſity of living in a conſtant and publick pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the whole faith, we muſt deny the honour of Martyrdom to thoſe who have dyed for it; we muſt reform our Kalendar, and raſe out the names of many who have hitherto en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd that glorious title upon Earth, and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs the Crown thereof in Heaven: But</p>
            <p n="3">3. We muſt follow the Lord with zeal and affection: if we are throughly perſuaded of our own duty, we muſt alſo be deſirous to ſee Gods Name glorified by others; and that not only with idle hopes and inſignificant deſires, but with active endeavours, and a real concern: 'Tis the glory of the Church of God to ſpread her arms abroad, like our Saviour on the Croſs, and receive all mankind within its embraces; his Blood was a ſufficient Atonement for all the world, and whoſoever neglects the means and opportunity of advancing this faith, betrays the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:96925:12"/> honour of Chriſt his head, and the ſalvation of his Fellow-members; he baſely ſuffers that ſoul for which our Saviour died, to periſh through unbelief, and makes the merits of his death to be ineffectual. If the late Martyrs, and unin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired Confeſſors of our faith, who planted a Church amongſt us with their ſweat, and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd it with their blood, had given way to prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of compliance and ſelf-preſervation, our Land had either continued barren to this day in its primitive Paganiſm, or been ſoon over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>run with Hereſie and Superſtition. Had the Prophet in my Text contented himſelf with a dormant Religion, and confin'd his faith to his own boſom, <hi>he</hi> might have enjoy'd his eaſe, and the <hi>Jews</hi> their Idolatry without the trouble of this fiery tryal. Yet ſuch was the zeal of <hi>Elijah</hi> for the Lord God of Hoſts, becauſe the Children of <hi>Iſrael had forſaken his Covenants, thrown down his Altars, and ſlain his Prophets with the ſword,</hi> that he reſtor'd his Religion with a mighty hand, and return'd that ſeverity upon the Prieſts of <hi>Baal,</hi> which they had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercis'd againſt the Servants of the living God: And I can never be perſuaded but that a <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying</hi> Chriſtian is a contradiction in the terms, till the communion of Saints be blotted out of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:96925:13"/> our Creed, and the Catholick Church be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated to conſiſt in the private breaſt of each particular Saint.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs, though a zeal for the Lord be our duty, and heroical vertue be moſt accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table in the eye both of God and man, yet it always happens, that where the greateſt honour is to be won, there is the greateſt danger, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we muſt be cautious:</p>
            <p n="1">1. That our zeal be according to knowledg, before we engage in the zealous defence of any cauſe, we muſt be well aſſur'd that the cauſe it ſelf be good, leſt inſtead of thanks for our dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, we receive a check for our forwardneſs, and it be juſtly ſaid unto us, <hi>Who has required theſe things at your hands?</hi> for if we have not ſufficient authority to warrant the action, it is not vertue, but raſhneſs to proceed; if we take a groundleſs opinion for our foundation, and make not reaſon our judge in the conſult, what aſſiſtance can we receive from it in the heat of action? we have then loſt all command of our ſelves, and ſhall be deaf to all advice; our igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance ſhall continue, but our vehemence, and conſequently our danger ſhall increaſe; we ſhall ſtill follow the ſame blind guide that firſt miſled our devotion, not knowing either how
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:96925:13"/> to ſtop our career or direct our courſe; like one that puts out to Sea without the aſſiſtance of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sails or Anchors; we lie at the mercy of every wind and tide, and are in danger of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing foundred upon every ſhallow, and ſplit up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on every Rock; therefore we muſt firſt beware of a <hi>blind miſguided zeal:</hi> But</p>
            <p n="2">2. We muſt be cautious alſo that our zeal be according to diſcretion, we muſt make allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances for the infirmities of our nature, and not extend our paſſions to the utmoſt pitch, like him that ſpreads all his ſayls for the ſpeedier expediting of his courſe, till at length for want of a due proportion of ballaſt he is over-power'd by the impetuouſneſs of the wind, and his Veſſel overſet: Therefore we muſt beware alſo of a <hi>fiery ungovernable</hi> zeal, and make reaſon our judge, not only of the ends we propoſe, but alſo of the means we uſe.</p>
            <p>The honour of God, and the defence of his worſhip are glorious undertakings; and yet even here, the exceſs of zeal is a crime, and the great importance of the end cannot juſtifie any unlawfulneſs in the means; the will of God, as it is expreſs'd in his word, is the Standard of good and evil, and he will not ſuffer his eternal Laws to be violated, though in his own defence.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:96925:14"/> If it ſhould pleaſe him to give his and our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies ſuch advantage over us as may endanger the exerciſe of our Religion, we have our prayers and other lawful endeavours for our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs; but we muſt not defend our Church by an unlawful return of evil for evil, nor like our Adverſaries, commit any act of impiety or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice, though under the moſt ſpecious pretence of fighting the battel of the Lord.</p>
            <p>The goodneſs of the cauſe here is ſo far from juſtifying the act, that it only aggravates the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence; for the ſins of a private circumſtance may much eaſier be forgiven, where the frailties of our nature or the violence of a temptation may leſſen the crime, and the obſcurity of the Author may remove the ſcandal. But when a Law is violated or any injuſtice done for the ſake of our Religion, both the ſcandal and the crime be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come conſpicuous, they are then laid at the doors of our Church and bring a publick and perpetual blot upon our cauſe. If God ſtands not in need of our vertues, much leſs does he ſtand in need of our ſins. If it pleaſe him to continue the light and truth of his Goſpel amongſt us, he can do it without any of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence or fault of ours, <hi>Si Pergama dextra defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di poſſent, etiam hac defenſa fuiſſent,</hi> with his own
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:96925:14"/> right Hand and with his holy Arm he will get himſelf the victory. But what can our Religion profit us, or what honour can it bring to the Almighty, when 'tis defended by ſuch means as diſhonour both God and Man; when our ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice comes polluted with blood and violence of its own, how can it attone for our tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions?</p>
            <p>Therefore it is neceſſary that we obey not only for wrath, but alſo for conſcience ſake. St. <hi>Peter</hi> who was the firſt that drew his Sword in his Maſters quarrel, was the firſt that deny'd his Name and forſook his cauſe; and doubtleſs who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever fights for his Religion againſt his Prince, can never paſs the muſter without a <hi>Romiſh</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation. It is not Piety but Faction that ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates his zeal, and like the unjuſt Steward he ſays, What ſhall I do? I cannot die for my Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and to comply I am aſham'd, therefore as Cowards do, he ſhuts his eyes againſt the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and the fear of Death makes him valiant; and if he dies in the cauſe, who would not ſooner ſet the brand of Hereſie upon his face than the Crown of Martyrdom upon his head?</p>
            <p>I wiſh this Diſcourſe were altogether as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent in theſe our days as I hope it is in this place, which ſeems to be ſtil'd the Metropolis
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:96925:15"/> of Piety and the center of Obedience, where Righteouſneſs and Peace do flouriſh, and Religion and Loyalty go hand in hand. And indeed it is only the practice of ſome miſguid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Zealots that can ſeparate them without an abſurdity; for no Man ever did or can follow the Lord to the tents of Rebellion; he always leads his people by the hands of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> and has given us Kings to go in and out before us, and whoſoever forſakes them forſakes alſo the Commandments of his God. Religion may be his pretence, and Godlineſs the Colours which he diſplays in his Banner, but 'tis Pride that whets his Sword, and Intereſt that makes it ready to the Battel: And to break Gods Law for the ſupport of his worſhip, is no leſs a contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction than to fight againſt a Prince in his own defence.</p>
            <p>Since therefore the heart of Man is deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful altogether, and we are ſubject to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret thoſe actions for the effects of Zeal, which are in truth the inſinuations of the Devil, I ſhall ſhew (3.) how we may know whether we <hi>follow the Lord</hi> or not.</p>
            <p>And I. If we truly zealous toward God we ſhall be zealous alſo for his Commandments; we muſt live in a conſtant intire obedience to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:96925:15"/> his will, without which our worſhip is in vain, and we may cry unto him, Lord, Lord, but he he will not hear; for what mercy can excuſe him who continually affront the God of mercy, or what power can ſave him who lives in defiance of that power which he acknowledges to be Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty? Not that every ſinful act proclaims us Traitors to the moſt High, and puts us out of the protection of his Law; as long as the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel of repentance, is in force, the unalterable decree of judgment does not paſs upon us; but while we continue in an habitual ſtate of ſin, and allow our ſelves the conſtant enjoyment of any one forbidden Luſt, ſo long we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt the will of God, and either queſtion his Truth who reveal'd the Law unto us, or deny his power of puniſhing the breach thereof; and therefore Saint <hi>James</hi> tells us, <hi>If we keep the whole Law, and yet offend in one point, we are guilty of all.</hi> And when the guilt of a uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal diſobedience lies upon us, we are ſurely very unfit to fight under the Banner of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But to avoid this fatal neceſſity, that they may ſtill indulge themſelves in their ſins without for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiting their Title to the Church, the men of this World have found out theſe two evaſions.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:96925:16"/>1. They advance the merits and neceſſity of Vertue in their Doctrine above meaſure, not for the ſake of God, but Mammon. They re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve the whole practice of Religion into Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality, and make good works the only means of Salvation; that when they have laid ſuch heavy burthens upon the people as neither they nor their forefathers were able to bear, they may abſolve them at their pleaſure, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe with them at their own rates: Thus they proſtitute their Temples again to the Money-changers, and make Merchandize of their Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity; and then how eaſie is it for a rich man to enter into the Kingdom of Heaven?</p>
            <p>But 2. This abuſe has produc'd the quite contrary extream in another ſort of men, that make Virtue utterly unneceſſary to the life of a Chriſtian, and confine all Religion to a bare relying upon the merits and mercies of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour: and becauſe God has predeſtinated ſome to be ſaved, they reſolve to put themſelves in the number, and regiſter themſelves Saints in ſpight of all their ſins; they work not out their ſalvation with fear and trembling, but with im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudence and preſumption make God the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of their ſins, and give him the whole trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of their ſalvation.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:96925:16"/>
            <p>And there are many ſuch that make great profeſſion of Zeal, and a noiſe about Religion, yet never trouble themſelves with the duties that Religion lays upon them: 'Tis this that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fanes the worſhip of God, and brings his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel into contempt: Not all the Blaſphemies of the Heathens, not all the Uſurpations of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, no, nor all the powers of the gates of Hell, can ſo far offend God, or prejudice his Church, as the ſcandalous practices of his falſe pretended Servants. The back-ſlidings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious, and ſhe plaid the Harlot upon every high Mountain, and under every green Tree; and yet for all this, the Lord ſaid, <hi>The back-ſliding</hi> Iſrael <hi>hath juſtifi'd her ſelf more than her treacherous Siſter</hi> Judah, <hi>who turn'd not unto me with her whole heart, but feignedly.</hi> We muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore firſt advance the Kingdom of God in our hearts, and ſeek his righteouſneſs, and then all theſe outward things, the beauty of holineſs, and the flouriſhing eſtate of a viſible Church ſhall be added unto us.</p>
            <p n="2">II. If we be truly zealous for the worſhip of God we ſhould alſo be zealous for the honour of his holy Name; we ſhould not with a ſordid com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance bear the reproaches which are daily caſt upon him, nor ſee his honour laid in the duſt by
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:96925:17"/> the prophaneneſs of every hypocritical preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Saint, and every lewd Atheiſtical unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever; we ſhould not with patience hear his Name traduc'd to authorize the ſacrilegious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellions of the one, and the impious exſecrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the other; but if our preſence cannot ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs, nor our exhortations reclaim their vice, we ſhould flie from the tents of wickedneſs, and avoid their company like an infected place.</p>
            <p n="3">III. We muſt be zealous alſo for the honour of Gods holy Temple. When we come into his Houſe, we muſt ſo behave our ſelves as ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit the Majeſty before whom we appear, and the place where his Honour dwells: We muſt here put off all Phariſaical greatneſs, and all diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled humiliation; all ſinful deſires, and all wandring idle thoughts; otherwiſe we profane that place which God has ſanctifi'd, and make his Service an unhallowed thing. The very laws of nature enforce a reverence from us to the places of devotion; and the Angels which here attend the prayers of the juſt, will certainly avenge the contempt of the profane. There is a reverence due even to miſguided piety; and Hiſtories relate unto us the Judgments which the juſt and true God has inflicted upon thoſe
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:96925:17"/> that defil'd the Temples of their own invented <hi>Deities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whatſoever therefore our Religion is, let us adorn it by an ingenuous profeſſion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; let our practice be according to the tenour of our faith; yea, and if <hi>Baal</hi> be God, let us fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him, which is the laſt part of my Text, and affords us theſe three conſiderations.</p>
            <p n="1">1. How the <hi>Jews</hi> came to doubt whether the Lord were God, or whether it were <hi>Baal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Since they did doubt, how ſhall we be aſſur'd hereof? And</p>
            <p n="3">3. Suppoſing the Lord to be God, yet what uſe may we make of the Prophets words, <hi>that if</hi> Baal <hi>be God then follow him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And 1. 'Tis ſtrange that the <hi>Jews</hi> ſhould ſo ſoon forget the Lord, after he had brought them out of <hi>Egypt</hi> with a ſtrong hand, and led them through the Wilderneſs with a ſtretched-out arm, that they could blot out the remembrance of his loving kindneſs, who cloath'd them by a miracle, and fed them with food from Heaven; 'tis ſtrange that this People, unto whom God had ſo often manifeſted both his goodneſs and his power, ſhould yet fall away from his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to follow a ſenſleſs Idol; yet this they did not out of any real belief of its divinity, but only
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:96925:18"/> to gratifie their luſts according to the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the Nations that were round about them. 'Twas the Religion of <hi>Baal</hi> to eat and drink, and riſe up to play: Whoredoms and Fornications are always the attendants of Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, and the worſhip proper to the Idol: for this cauſe it was that the <hi>People bow'd down unto them, and threreout they ſuck no ſmall advantage.</hi> Whilſt men of vitious inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and impotent reaſons, indulge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in their ſenſual Luſts, there will not be wanting thoſe that ſhall bow the knee to <hi>Baal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How far the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks have made uſe of this policy to eſtabliſh their Church, is notorious to all the world; how they comply with every ones inclinations, and allow the worſt of men in their ſins: for their intereſt they can indulge, and incourage too the higheſt enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, and live upon the ſins of the People. 'Tis this that brings ſuch crowds of Nations to their Temples, and makes their Altars ſmoke; 'tis not the probability of their faith, nor the antientneſs of their traditions that has advanc'd their cauſe; but the looſeneſs of their doctrines, and the liberty of their practices; the eaſie penances enjoyn'd to ſinners in their lives, and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:96925:18"/> the ample indulgences allow'd them at their deaths.</p>
            <p>Thus they egregiouſly promote a Chriſtian Church, by deſtroying Chriſtianity it ſelf, and ſet up a faith of their own that makes void both the Law and the Prophets, and fruſtrates the deſign of all Religion: And now they may take to themſelves their boaſted Univerſality, and glory that their doctrine is not only Preach'd, but Practis'd too throughout the world; for whilſt ſin is the univerſal diſtemper of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, 'tis to be fear'd that <hi>Rome</hi> will be the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church.</p>
            <p n="2">2. How ſhall we know whether the Lord be God, or whether it be <hi>Baal?</hi> We do not now expect the ſpirit of <hi>Elijah</hi> to reprove us, nor fire from Heaven to convince our unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief; and yet God has not left himſelf without teſtimonies, even in theſe our days, ſufficient to aſſert the truth of his Religion. I ſhall men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion only two which are grounded upon the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of my Text.</p>
            <p n="1">1. We have our <hi>Reaſon</hi> for our judge; exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine and try whether the Lord be not God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, and whether there be any deceitfulneſs in him: ſearch the records of time, and ſee if there be any that can perform thoſe wondrous
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:96925:19"/> works which he hath done; his truth will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure the ſevereſt tryal, and he needs not the ignorance of his Servants to advance their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions, but delights in the underſtanding of his Saints, and requires a reaſonable ſervice. If <hi>Baal</hi> be God, then in Gods name follow <hi>Baal.</hi> The Prophet does not impoſe his own ſenſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, nor magiſterially dictate his own opinion, but gives them commiſſion to make uſe of their reaſon, and the freedom of their judgment in the ſearch, and only requires them to make a return according as they find the proof.</p>
            <p>Not like the practices of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which requires an implicit faith to their uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivable devices, and ties us up to all the dictates of their infallible Judge; that confines all knowledge to the mouth of the Prieſt, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows not ſo much as the evidence of opinion to the people: Surely the light was made to ſhine, and the Goſpel was given us to profit withal, but their concealments are an argument of their guilt; and if <hi>Rome</hi> muſt ſtill be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ground, it is not now to avoid the perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of tyranny, but the convictions of truth it ſelf.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:96925:19"/>
            <p>This is the firſt argument of the truth of a Religion from the Reaſonableneſs of it; the ſecond ſhall be taken from its <hi>Succeſs:</hi> It was this iſſue upon which <hi>Elijah</hi> put the grand de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate between him and the Prieſts of <hi>Baal;</hi> he pray'd, and God heard his voice; he believ'd, and therefore it happened unto him according to his faith; and the fire came down from Heaven to conſume his Sacrifice. God has in all ages ſhew'd an eſpecial regard to his Church, and with the watchful eye of providence has directed all its motions. How miraculous were the advances of Chriſtianity in the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive times, when all the powers of the world ſet themſelves with fire and ſword to oppoſe its progreſs? How wonderfully have thoſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corrupted ſtreams of truth been deriv'd to us through all the ſeas of violence and falſhood, with which it has continually encountred? and 'tis no leſs a miracle that we ſtill continue in the true worſhip of God, though compaſs'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with our Adverſaries on every ſide; that our Church ſtill retains the purity of its do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, notwithſtanding the perpetual aſſaults of Superſtition and Idolatry, and the ſecret underminings of Hereſie and Schiſm; which is a great proof that God has eſpous'd the cauſe
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:96925:20"/> of our Church, ſince no weapon has proſper'd that was lifted up againſt it.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, that an evil cauſe alſo may be ſupported for a ſeaſon by the force of evil arms, and therefore I ſhould not inſiſt upon this argument in our defence, but that there are ſtill amongſt us thoſe who formerly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd it to our deſtruction; men of ſo poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick a faith, that they could meaſure the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their cauſe by the number of their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herents, and thought a Victory did ſufficiently juſtifie a Rebellion; they had no plea for break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down all the fences of human ſociety, and violating the Ordinances of both God and man, but the dictates of their private ſpirit, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret correſpondence with God: and they had no proof of this their Almighty commiſſion and correſpondence, but from the ſucceſs of their arms: then they boaſted themſelves of their Victory, and were exalted in their ſtrength; and as they made God the Author of their ſins, ſo in frequent thankſgivings they gave him the praiſe of its ſucceſs: But bleſſed be God, our Religion, as it was founded upon no blood, but that of our Saviour, ſo it was reſtor'd to us from the uſurpation of theſe men in peace, has hitherto flouriſh'd in the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:96925:20"/> truth, and I hope will be ſupported by God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs.</p>
            <p>But thirdly: Suppoſing the Lord to be God, yet we may make ſome uſe of the Prophets words, that <hi>if</hi> Baal <hi>be God we muſt follow him.</hi> From theſe worſhippers of <hi>Baal,</hi> we may in ſome ſort learn how to follow the <hi>living God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis a ſhame to our Religion that we ſhould go to the Heathens for examples of vertue, and learn piety of an Idolater; and yet if we obſerve the devotion of theſe Prieſts of <hi>Baal,</hi> and other Enemies of our profeſſion, we ſhall find ſuch ſtrains of zeal amongſt them, as may ſerve, though not for our imitation, yet for our reproach. How did they <hi>cry aloud from morning even until noon, and cut themſelves after their manner with Knives and Lancets, till the blood guſhed out upon them.</hi> How do others alſo make it a piece of their Religion to riſe up at mid-night to their Prayers, and awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken their devotion with cords and thongs? How did <hi>thoſe</hi> Idolaters make their Children paſs through the fire to <hi>Moloch?</hi> How do <hi>theſe</hi> alſo ſacrifice not only their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, but their Parents alſo, their Kings and Princes to their devotion? If their zeal
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:96925:21"/> could force them voluntarily to do violence to their natures, cannot we at the command of God himſelf uſe ſuch neceſſary ſelf-denyal, ſuch moderate abſtinence and faſting, as may fit and prepare us for his reaſonable ſervice? if they to ſerve their Idols, could force their way through all the bounds of humanity, and follow their God as the <hi>Jews</hi> follow'd our Saviour, with Swords and Staves? Cannot we ſubmit to the juſt and eaſie commands of the Almighty? for <hi>what does he require of thee, O Man, but to do juſtly, to love mercy, and to walk humbly with thy God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſum of all is this: <hi>Let us no longer halt between two opinions,</hi> but if God has ſet up his Standard in <hi>Rome</hi> for an Enſign of the People, to which all the Gentiles ſhould ſeek, let us no longer conceal our duty, nor delay our holy Pilgrimage, but make our way with Fire and Sword; let us give the reins to our luſts, and commit all iniquity with greedineſs, that the vehemence of our paſſions, and the greatneſs of our ſins, may add ſtrength to our faith, and ſincerity to our repentance; as if they loved moſt who had moſt need to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:96925:21"/>
            <p>Or if God had withdrawn his preſence from our ſolemn Congregations, and ſhrouded his glory in the private retir'd Aſſemblies; if the beauty of holineſs conſiſts in an unſeemly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpectful ſervice, and the liberty of the Goſpel leaves us to our own devices; If diſſimulation and familiarity with our God be a virtue, and Rebellion againſt our Prince be the great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment, then let us be zealous in this work of the Lord, and drive on furiouſly towards confuſion; let us once more bind our Kings in chains, and our Nobles in fetters of iron.</p>
            <p>But if theſe things are an abomination, and there can be no communion betwixt God and <hi>Baal,</hi> then my beloved Brethren, be ye ſtead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt and unmoveable, always abounding in the work of the Lord, for as much as ye know tha: your labour is not in vain. If the Lord be God follow him in the worſhip of his Name, with boldneſs and reſolution; follow him in your lives with zeal and affection, and be ye con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant unto death. Let neither Tribulation nor Anguiſh, Principalities nor Powers, things pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, nor things to come, ſeparate us from the love of God, or ſhake our reſolutions. Let neither the temptations of the fleſh, nor the evil cuſtoms of the wicked world induce us to take
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:96925:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> part with the deſtroyer: but let our good works ſhine like lights before men, to the glory of God, and the confirmation of his Church. Let our ways be upright, as amongſt the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and our converſation unblamable, to ſtop the mouths of of gain-ſayers; and let our faith o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome the world, and tread down Satan un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our feet; for this is a Chriſtians triumph, theſe are the badges of our profeſſion, and muſt be our Crowns and Diadems, when dignities and diſtinctions ſhall be no more. Without theſe it is but vanity to expect, and injuſtice to demand the honour due to the Servants of the Lord, when our Vices ſhal level us with the worſhippers of <hi>Baal.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
